September 1, 1939. Nazi Germany invades Poland, marking the beginning of
World War II. In May of the following year, the Germans inaugurated the camp
Auschwitz concentration camp, located about 60 kilometers west of Krakow. The direct reason
The creation of the camp is due to the fact that mass arrests of Poles are increasing.
beyond the capacity of existing "local" prisons. In October 1941,
The Nazis begin construction of Birkenau, which will become the largest of the more than 40
camps and subcamps that make up the Auschwitz complex. Since March 1942, Auschwitz-Birkenau
plays a central role in the German effort to kill the Jews of Europe
Approximately one million people (probably about 90 percent of
the victims of the Auschwitz concentration camp) will die there. From August 1942
Until the evacuation of the camp in January 1945, one of the inmates of Birkenau was a young woman
Slovak who will eventually become the leader of the camp, responsible for 30,000 prisoners and who
will use her position to save thousands of women from the gas chambers. Her name is Magda Hellinger.
Magda Hellinger, 25, arrived at the main camp at Auschwitz
on the second transport from Slovakia at the end of March 1942.
In August of that same year, the prisoners were transferred
to a facility located just over 3 kilometers away called Birkenau.
There Magda's role was to supervise the cleaning of the barracks to maintain
hygiene and bringing prisoners bread, margarine and soup, if there was stock.
When Magda selected her team of helpers and went to collect the bread, a young and pretty guard
A German SS woman with long braids was watching her so she called her over and asked:
“What is your name?” Magda replied and also asked the German SS woman what her name was.
called. The guard answered “Irma,” to which Magda replied that she was delighted to meet her.
It was Irma Grese, who would later be known as the Hyena of Auschwitz. From this
At their first meeting, the two called each other simply Magda and Irma.
It was always dangerous for the SS to find typhus in a barracks. When the Germans
If they found out that a prisoner in a barracks had this disease, they would send them all to
the gas chamber. Magda and thirty other Slovak girls were also infected. However,
Her fellow inmates cared for her and covered her during the time she was ill. In the end
survived, but soon contracted malaria. This time the girls decided it was better for
Magda wanted to stay in the hospital, but the rats ran and bit her fingers.
and the feet of the women, some of whom were probably dead,
Magda asked to be discharged, arguing that "there are better ways to die." They took her
to the barracks and that same day Magda learned that shortly after her departure,
All the hospital's occupants had been sent to the crematorium's gas chamber.
One day, about 300 French women were taken to the camp. Magda was chosen to
to be their “barracks elder” and take care of them. They were political prisoners, mostly doctors,
lawyers and intellectuals. When Magda said, “I don’t speak French,” Katya, her superior,
responded with a direct "now yes!" Magda took charge of them, helping those
women in every way she could until they were deported to Ravensbrück. At that time Magda
He didn't know that these women would later play a crucial role in his survival.
Magda was later responsible for a new group of Polish women. Maria Mandl,
SS-Lagerführerin of the women's camp, arranged for Magda's transfer to Block 10,
which was an experimental barracks located in the main camp. It was completely closed
and isolated from the surrounding countryside. The windows were covered with wooden boards so that
no one could see inside or outside. To alleviate the conditions of poor women,
Magda demanded sheets, pillows, blankets, towels, and soap from doctor Eduard Wirths.
The operations were performed on girls without anesthesia and Magda heard their cries,
pleas and screams of agony. A Jewish doctor named Samuel refused to operate on these women.
only to perform experiments and was sent to the gas chamber.
On one occasion, 30 women were taken to a sanatorium where German doctors
They wanted to conduct studies on their brains, which meant they would have to kill them first.
Magda helped two of the women escape. As a result, she was taken to Hans Aumeier,
the deputy commandant of the camp. The next day, Irma Grese, on the orders of Maria Mandl, took
Magda to the standing cell of block 11, where she could not lie down, only stand. In this
permanent cell, Magda and 3 other women spent 7 long nights. They could not move, not even the
head. Every morning, they were released for roll call. Irma told Magda to go outside,
to lie down quickly and rest a little before roll call. To Irma Grese, who was extremely
sadistic with the other prisoners, she liked Magda and helped her. During the day, she was supposed to
that Magda cleaned the latrines, but as she was weak, other prisoners helped her leaving her
sleep and did the work for her. When the Nazi guards arrived, they would wake her up.
Magda survived and was later promoted to block elder or block leader of 300
Slovak girls. She got them blankets from Canada Warehouse, which were used to store
the stolen belongings of the arriving prisoners. As it got colder,
Slovak girls tore these blankets to cover themselves. When the SS personnel
He found out, at first they wanted to send the girls to the crematorium, but Magda told the Lagerführer
Johann Schwarzhuber that the women were cold and were simply trying to warm themselves. After
After some discussion, he ordered that hundreds of dresses be delivered to the women the following day.
One day, Magda was taken to the hospital to be sterilized with radiation. However,
The Jewish doctor's assistant told the SS doctors that all the pipes in
water were frozen and could not be sterilized. This would
gave Magda some time before Margot Dreschel, another guard at the Auschwitz camp,
who was informed of what was happening, intervened and let Magda leave the hospital.
In May 1944, Josef Kramer, the commandant of Auschwitz-Birkenau, told Magda the following:
"Here is camp C and you will be the oldest of the Lagers." Magda replied. "If you want me to be there,
Here, I want beds with straw bags, blankets, plates to eat on and wooden spoons.” He said
that it was fine and that "you will receive it tomorrow." The next day, Hungarian transports arrived
and the population of Camp C soon increased to 30,000 women. The SS camp leader was
became Irma Grese. Magda formed a group of informants with girls around 14 years old and sent them
to the barracks to look for doctors. 64 doctors came, and Magda assigned them to different barracks.
To monitor the girls' health and look for the first signs of an epidemic, Magda decided
that any prisoner who showed the first signs of an epidemic would be locked up in small
rooms at the rear of the barracks. Soon an epidemic of scarlet fever began.
Since Magda knew that Irma would send the women to the gas chambers, she told her: “Irma,
It's very hot. Sit on the chair in the living room while I take the roll call alone." Magda took the roll call
for 6 weeks until the scarlet fever epidemic ended. Hundreds of women were saved.
Irma Grese, who treated Magda like an older sister,
She even asked him what he thought of her new boyfriend, whom she had introduced him to herself.
In the summer of 1944, among the women deported from Hungary to Auschwitz-Birkenau was
Dr. Gisella Perl. Gisella approached Magda and told her that she had been observing the shape
how he handled things in the place and that I admired the humanity with which he organized
to 30,000 women. Gisella also explained to Magda that she was a gynecologist and that she had worked in
a sanatorium in Romania. When an order came from above demanding that all women
Pregnant women had to come in for registration and be sent to a sanatorium,
Magda sent her runners to let the women know that no pregnant woman should
come forward because the sanatorium story was a lie. Over the next few months,
To save the lives of pregnant women, Dr. Perl performed numerous abortions.
Dr. Josef Mengele, who made random selections on the train platform, often came
to the camp barracks for selection. The selected girls had to go to the front,
where the trucks were waiting to take them to the gas chambers. One day,
After Mengele left, Magda, looking for the SS guards, stood between them.
who were walking towards the trucks, he separated a group and simply marched them away.
return to the barracks. No one noticed and the girls were saved. The next time Dr.
Mengele arrived at the barracks and selected a large number of young women and left again,
Magda again stepped in between and told them to follow her,
saving the girls. After that, he would repeat the trick every time he saw the opportunity.
However, Magda's greatest act of courage came when Mengele selected 800 girls
to send them to the gas chamber. Mengele left and the girls were sent to Block 3,
where they were guarded by a young German SS guard who would be sent to the Front
Russian the next day. Magda managed to get a bottle of alcohol and together with her assistant Gerda
They got the German guard drunk. During the night, after he fell asleep,
The two women took the girls from Block 3 to eight other barracks in the
who ordered the Block elder to find space for these women. Each
Once they took a group of a hundred, in five rows so as not to attract attention. To their surprise,
The Germans didn't notice and Magda, Gerda and a bottle of alcohol saved 800 girls.
The day before the roll call, two runners arrived with four women, whose breasts had
been opened after Irma Grese hit them with her whip. After Magda
took care of the women, he told Irma: “Imagine if someone did that to you.
"What a shame." At that moment, Irma raised her whip towards Magda who said: "Hit,
Hit me, I know you like to see blood. I'm offended." After Magda walked away,
Irma went after her and said in a low voice: “Forgive me.”
One day Irma approached Magda and said, “Magda, come with me to the men’s camp.” When
Magda asked her why she needed her for that, Irma replied: “If you come,
"It's official business. When can you go?" Magda told her messengers to ask
to women if they had husbands, brothers, fathers or sons in the men's camp.
The women wrote their messages with their block numbers and folded the papers and
Magda's messengers returned these pieces of paper to her. Magda then handed the notes to the
recipients and the men responded on the other side of the paper. Irma took Magda to a
similar excursion to the men's camp two other times and Magda made the most of it each time.
One day, the doctor Fritz Klein told the Hungarian girls in perfect Hungarian:
"Why should you be in this camp? I'll send you to the sanatorium. There's everything there, even
“Good food, clean and good.” Everyone wanted to go. Magda intervened and said, “If I can be here,
you too.” Then he said to Klein, “Commander Kramer will be very angry with you.
"Leave now and don't try that again!" Outside, the truck was waiting, ready to take
the girls not to the sanatorium but to the gas chamber. There was absolute hysteria when the girls,
Unaware of what awaited them, they wanted to leave and Magda, who knew the truth,
had to slap some girls to stop the panic. However,
The girls didn't believe Magda and never thanked her for saving their lives.
In early January 1945, Soviet forces approached the complex of the
Auschwitz concentration camp and the SS began evacuating Auschwitz
and its subcamps. These forced marches of concentration camp prisoners were
became known as the death marches. News quickly spread that the
The Russians were approaching and on January 18, 1945, the inmates, including Magda, were sent
to one of these death marches. It was terribly cold. Half of the people who started
the journey lay on the road, murdered by the German SS or had died of hunger and
starvation. After countless days, Magda and other prisoners arrived at Ravensbrück. The
French women, whom Magda had previously cared for at Auschwitz, were
alerted that Magda was there. They gave her a hot shower and let her sleep in a bed.
Magda had diarrhea and the girls gave her clean pajamas and medicine. They told her that she would never
They would forget how he had behaved with them in Auschwitz and when Magda had to move to
Malchow camp, had recovered. The French girls had saved his life.
Eventually, Magda and other prisoners ended up in Malchow, one of Ravensbrück's subcamps.
The prisoners were guarded by SS guards and their German shepherd dogs. The SS
They were very cruel, but probably one of Malchow's toughest guards was Luise Danz who
became commander of the camp. Magda befriended Danz trying to stop his
cruelty and in a conversation, Danz told him that he had a brother on the eastern front and
who was very worried about him. Magda decided to use this information and asked Danz
if he wanted to meet with a Romani fortune teller to tell him what was happening to his
Brother. Magda arranged the meeting and informed the fortune teller about their previous conversation.
with Danz. The fortune teller then said to Danz: “Your brother is thinking about you and is very worried,
for what's happening and what you're doing. Hope you're okay
when the war is over." Later, Danz's behavior became less cruel.
On another occasion Magda asked Danz if he wanted a portrait of herself. Afterwards
Before she accepted, Magda told Edith, a fellow inmate who was a good artist,
to paint a portrait of Luise Danz. The idea was that it would take a long time to do,
hoping to keep her away from the camp area and beat the women.
On April 24, 1945, the SS guards disappeared and the women
were liberated shortly after by the Soviets. A few days later,
They learned that World War II had ended.
Magda then returned home to Michalovce to confirm whether any of her relatives were still alive.
His brother Ernest, the partisan, was already home. However, his parents and his brother Artur,
as well as 150 other members of the Hellinger family, died in the Holocaust.
Magda was soon told that Bela Blau, a man she had met at Auschwitz,
had been there two weeks ago. Soon a letter arrived in which Bela asked Magda to
went to Žilina, located in the northwestern part of present-day Slovakia. Although he hesitated because
I didn't really know him, it was just the same. When the two met in Žilina,
Bela happily picked up Magda and ran with her around the room. The two decided
embark on the next part of their life together and soon their daughter Maya was born. After eighteen
months were blessed with another daughter, named Eva. Magda was happy to have daughters because
She was afraid that a child would remind Bela of the loss of her beloved son Ervin,
five years old, murdered along with Bela's wife, Irma, in the gas chamber at Auschwitz.
Magda and Béla opened a fabric shop and haberdashery in the Czech town of Rumburk until
that his business was confiscated in 1948, when the Communist Party took over Czechoslovakia.
The following year the family moved to Israel and in 1956 to Australia. It was a
difficult time for a young family, they had almost no money and had to start from scratch
zero. Over time, they worked in men's clothing retail.
In 1953, the following article by Dr. Gisella Perl was published in a Hungarian language newspaper
from Tel Aviv in which he praised Magda saying: “Our Lagerälteste, our Magda, was a
righteous person. She fought like a righteous person. I thank providence that our Magda was
So, someone who believed and had faith that one day we would be human again. Someone who,
Everywhere and at all times, he helped us with kindness, defended us and saved us, sometimes with
hardness and sometimes smiling or frowning. I feel that with this testimony I am settling a
debt of gratitude on behalf of many, many prisoners (and not least on my own behalf)
name) to whom Magda, the Lagerälteste of Auschwitz-Birkenau, had shown so much kindness.”
For many years, journalists, historians and students approached Magda in search of
of information about her stay at Auschwitz. She thought they would be writing her story.
However, they were researching for their own projects. Magda was disappointed,
so he decided to write his own story and after doing so, he took his manuscript without
edited for printing. So he felt like his story had been told. Years later,
His daughter Maya felt that there were many vital details that were omitted in
his book and decided to rewrite the story with more research. The resulting book,
called: “The Nazis knew my name”, has been very successful and has been translated into 13 languages.
languages. Today, the story Magda always wanted to tell is known around the world.
Until her last days, Magda Hellinger spoke of her experiences to make sure
that the world never forgets and learns from what happened to her and her family.
In the book, Magda writes: “My number is 2,318. Under this number I survived and endured
Dehumanization, beatings, and screams. I suffered all kinds of illnesses. Against all odds, I lived through three
years and a half, first in the main camp at Auschwitz and then in Birkenau. Why do I start?
Now to tell my story? There are people who, for reasons beyond my understanding, try
deny that the Holocaust existed. Didn't we suffer enough to have to listen now?
such denials? I cannot undo what was done to me and many others. The torments and
Nightmares wake me up every night when I close my eyes. So I turn to you.
– readers, parents, teachers, preachers, professors, scientists, priests – for
to educate children and the public about the horrors perpetrated under the Nazi regime. Some
Things can't be changed, but we must end this denial. I was there, I witnessed it!
Magda's husband, Béla, died on September 2, 2002, at the age of 92.
When Magda died on June 29, 2006, she was 89 years old. Magda's revenge is not
only that she survived and taught about the hardships she endured during the Holocaust
until his last days, but despite the fact that the Nazis wanted to kill all the Jews,
His legacy and courage will continue. And this will be done not only through his two children and four grandchildren,
but also through the families of thousands of women whom he saved from a
certain death. These women maintained contact with Magda until her last day.
Many tears were shed for Magda Hellinger.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to like and subscribe
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss out
our next videos thanks See you next time on the fore channel